Guide to the Hopkins Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hopkins family papers
1778-1933
1875-1933
MS 290
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes, 1 folio)
Papers of Edward Washburn Hopkins (1857-1932), professor of Sanskrit and comparative philology at Yale; and Clark Hopkins, member of the classics department and director of the Dura-Europos expeditions with smaller amounts of material on Allen Hopkins, Edward Lewis Hopkins (1898-), Francis Washburn Hopkins, (1896-), Samuel Hopkins (1756-1782), and Edward Allen Low (d.1880). The Edward Washburn Hopkins papers contain writings on religion in India and classical Greece and the Clark Hopkins papers have an essay and photographs on excavations in Syria.
Hopkins family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
EDWARD WASHBURN HOPKINS, 1857-1932 *
Francis Washburn Hopkins, "Frank," "Hop," "Fritz," was born December 29, 1896, in Halle, Germany, but he spent most of his life in New Haven, Connecticut. His father, Edward Washburn Hopkins, was born September 8, 1857, in Northampton, Massachussetts; and was graduated from Columbia University in 1878. He received the following degrees: Ph.D. from the University of Leipsic in 1881; LL.D from Columbia University in 1902, and Ph.D. from the University of Athens in 1912. He has spent most of his life in New Haven where he is professor of Sanskrit and comparative philology at Yale University. Mary Sanger (Clark) Hopkins was a resident of New York City before her marriage. There are five sons and one daughter in the family. Yale relatives include three brothers, Clark Hopkins, '17, Edward L. Hopkins, '19, and Howard Hopkins, '21; and his sister, Pauline Hopkins, who attended the School of Fine Arts in 1916-1917.
*Excerpted from the biographical sketch of his son, Francis Washburn Hopkins, History of the Class of 1918, Yale College, Vol. I, p185.
* * * * *
Further information from the Historical Register of Yale University, 1701-1937:
CLARK HOPKINS
B.A. 1917, PH.D. Univ. of Wisconsin 1924, B.A. and M.A. Univ. of Oxford 1926. Instructor in Latin 1924-1925; Instructor in Greek 1925-1927; Sterling Fellow in Classical Languages 1927-1928; Research Associate in Greek and Latin (Asst. Prof. rank) 1928-1929; Asst. Professor of Classics 1929-1931; Curator of the Antiquities from Dura and Gerasa 1929-1936; Field Director of Excavations (Asst. Prof rank) 1931-1935.
EDWARD WASHBURN HOPKINS
B.A. Columbia Univ. 1878, DR.PHIL. Univ of Leipsic 1881, M.A. (Hon.) Yale Univ. 1895, LL.D. Columbia Univ. 1902, LL.D. Univ of Athens 1912. Professor of Sanskrit and Comparative Philology 1895-1919; Edward E. Salisbury Professor of Sanskrit and Comparative Philology 1919-1926; Professor Emeritus 1926-1932; Trowbridge Memorial Lecturer 1913-1914, 1916-1917.
FRANCIS WASHBURN HOPKINS
B.A 1918, LL.B. Fordham Univ. 1925, PH.D. Yale Univ. 1930. Assistant in Instruction (1st term) 1928-1929; Instructor in Political Economy 1929-1931.
Archaeology; Greece -- Civilization; Classical education; Families; Linguistics; India -- Religion; Syria -- Antiquities; Archaeologists; Classicists; Educators; Philologists; Hopkins, Edward Washburn, 1857-1932; Hopkins, Francis Washburn, 1896-; Hopkins, Samuel, 1756-1782; Hopkins family; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1778, 1875-1933
  - Edward Washbrun Hopkins (1857-1932)
    - Notebook containins student orations, 1876-1877 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Journal, 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Review of O. Gruppe, Die Griechischen Culte..., [post-1885] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Review of H. M. Chadwick, The Heroic Age, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lectures on Buddhism, 1913-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Manuscript, "History of Hindu Theism", 1919-1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lecture, "Buddhist Mysticism", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Legends of India
      - Manuscript (pp. 1-364), [1928?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Manuscript (pp. 365-506), [1928?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Typescript, [1928?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Typescript and reprint, "The Oath in Hindu Epic Literature", [1931-1933] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Essay, "Recent Discussions of Primitive Aryan Culture" (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Essay, "Polo a Thousand Years Ago", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Notes, "SK Lit", undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Play, "A Strong Hand", undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Essay, "The Relation of Greek Architecture to Modern", undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Essay, "Relation of Greek Drama to modern Drama", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Notebook, "Rig Veda/ VIII Mandalam", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Essay, "Comparative Syntax", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Essay, "Excursus: The Divine Physician" (fragment), undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Essay, "Relation of Greek Culture to Modern Life: Attitude toward Life", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Essay, "Impressions of American Education", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Essay, "Impressions of Oxford", undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Notebook on classical and philosophical subjects, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Poems and miscellaneous writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Columbia College certificates, 1875-1878 (Box 5)
  - Allen Hopkins: Birthday book, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Clark Hopkins
    - Essay, "The Old and the New on the Syrian Euphrates", 1933 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - List of photographs for "The Old and the New on the Syrian Euphrates", undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Photographs for "The Old and the New on the Syrian Euphrates", undated (Box 3, Folder 28 - 38)
    - School notebooks contaning copies of poems and notes on the Bible, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Edward Lewis Hopkins (1898-): notebooks on papermaking and prospective customers, [1921-1923?] (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Francis Washburn Hopkins: notebook on military topics, [1917-1918?] (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Samuel Hopkins (1756-1782 Y 1777): ALS to Lydia Hall, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Edward Allen Low, Jr. (d. 1880): notebook of poems, 1875-1879 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Account book of sporting goods sales, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Poems for children, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)